嘿，你们好，我是TheCherno，欢迎回到我的OpenGL系列教程
hey, what's up guys, my name is TheCherno, and welcome back to my OpenGL series
那么今天我们会讲OpenGL中的纹理
so today we're gonna be talking all about textures in OpenGL
我将从定义纹理到底是什么开始
I'm gonna start by defining what exactly a texture is
所以当大多数人想到纹理的时候
so when most people think of textures
他们真的只会想到在一个游戏中的3D对象上呈现图像
they really just think of having an image on a 3D object in a game
当然，不一定非得是3D对象
it doesn't have to be a 3D object of course
而你们在PS或画图等等中创建的图像
but some kind of image that you've created in something, like photoshop, a paint or whatever
让它出现在你们的图形应用程序中
having that on some kind of surface in your graphical application
那就是纹理的本质
that is essentially what a texture is
或者至少是大部分人眼中的纹理
or at least that's how most people actually kind of think of a texture
现在，除了这些，关于纹理的理解，比我刚才描述的要多得多
now, beyond that textures can really be, a lot more than just what I just described
纹理可以用于很多事情
textures can be used really for a lot of things
当我们讲到一些非常复杂的图形技术时，我们会发现那些
and we'll discover that, when we get into some pretty complicated graphics techniques
但现在我只想让你们把纹理看作是我们可以使用的图像
but for now I just want you to think about a texture as essentially an image that we can use
当我们渲染一些东西的时候
when we're rendering something
那么我实际能做的就是设计或创造某种图像
so what I can actually do is design or create some kind of image
不管是一张照片，还是画布上的一条弯弯曲曲的线
whether that be a photograph or maybe just a squiggly line on a canvas
或者是纯色或者类似的颜色，任何类似的颜色
or maybe like a kind of solid color or something like that, anything like that
我可以在我的电脑中创建任何图像文件，然后把它上传到我的显存中
I can create any image file in my computer, and then I can actually upload it to my GPU's memory
然后在我的着色器中使用它来绘制我现在正在做的任何东西
and use that in my shader for whatever kind of drawing I'm doing now
这可能像在我们的OpenGL程序中画一个矩形一样简单
this might be something as simple as just drawing a rectangle in our OpenGL program
它包含了渲染纹理的元素，这样我们就可以在游戏中看到纹理
the contained that is actually rendering that texture, so that we can see the texture in our game
或者也可能是更复杂的东西
or it might be something a lot more complicated
就像使用预先计算好的数学值，将其融入到我们的纹理中
like using kind of prep calculated mathematical values, that are baked into our texture
然后在着色器中对它们进行采样
and then being able to sample them in our shader
这样我们可以做一些很酷的灯光效果，但现在
so that we can do some cool lighting effects, but for now
它只会在OpenGL应用中从计算机获取图像到表面
it's just going to be getting an image from our computer onto a surface in our OpenGL application
那么让我们来看看我们都有什么
so let's take a look at what we've got here
如果我们现在启动应用
so if we launch our application right now
这样我们就能想起我们到底在哪里了
just so that we can remember where we're actually at
你们会看到我们有这样一个动态颜色的矩形
you'll see that we just had this kind of rectangle with a pulsating color
现在我们今天能做的
now what we're going to do today
实际上就是在那个矩形上绘制一个纹理，取代这种纯色
is actually draw a texture on that rectangle, instead of this kind of solid color
现在如果我看这个OpenGL程序的实际目录
now if I look at my actual directory for this OpenGL program
我已经创建了这个res文件夹，在那个里面，有个textures文件夹
I've made this resources folder, and inside there, I've made a folder called textures
只有一张单独的图片
which just has a single image
就是我这里的这个ChernoLogo
and it's going to be this ChernoLogo that I have here
这就是我们要在程序中那个矩形上绘制的东西
this is what we're actually going to draw on top of that rectangle that we have in our program
那么我们如何实现那个
so how do we do that
我们如何从电脑上的物理png文件转变过来
how do we go from having a physical kind of png file on our computer
才能在着色器中进行采样
to actually being able to sample it in our shader
我们可以把它绘制在屏幕上，它是怎么工作的
so that we can draw it on the screen, how does that work
第一步，我们需要以某种方式将图像加载到CPU内存中，对吧
well step one is we need to load that image somehow into our CPU memory, right
那么在这个例子中，它是一张png图片
so in this case, it's a png
现在我不打算深入讨论，在游戏中如何使用纹理以及它的格式化
now I'm not going to get into, how games use textures and what formats that
所有那些都在游戏引擎系列中，png并未真正用于游戏引擎中
all that will see for the game engine series, png is aren't really used in game engine
由于各种原因，大多数游戏引擎都有自己的纹理格式
most game engines have their own texture format for various reasons
但现在，这都是关于载入OpenGL的
but for now, just because again this is all about loading OpenGL
我们有一个png图像文件，我们需要以某种方式加载它
we do have a png image file, so what we need to do is load that somehow
现在png格式不是特别复杂
now png format isn't particularly complicated
但这儿有几种
but there are a few kind of
有一些不同的像素格式
there are a few different pixel formats inside there
以及主要有一个压缩png的选项
as well as primarily the option of having a compressed png as well
这里有很多解码，我们需要把数据取出来
and there's a bunch of decoding that, we actually need to do get the data out
所以我们要做的是使用一个库来实现那个
so what we're going to do is we're going to use a library for that
特别地，我们将使用stb_image库
and specifically, we're going to use something called stb_image
这是一个非常非常小的文件
which is a very very small one file
那就是我们要做的一切
that's all we're going to do
我们马上就能得到它
we're going to get it from get in a second here
但我们所需要的真就是一个文件
but all we need really is one file
实际上，我们会用它来加载png
and we're going to use that to actually load the png
当我说加载png时，我的意思是我们给它一个文件路径
now when I say load the png what I mean is we give it a file path
所以这就是我电脑里的文件
so this is my file in my computer
它会给我们
and what it's going to do is give us
基本上就是一个指向RGBA像素缓冲区的指针，这就是我们想要的
basically a pointer to a buffer of RGBA pixels, which is what we actually want to
然后进行下一步
then take to the next step
我们会取那个像素数组，然后把它上传到我们的显卡
we're just going to be taking that pixel array, and uploading it to our GPU
我们实现那个的方式当然就是通过OpenGL
and the way that we do that of course is through OpenGL
因为OpenGL是我们的图形规范
because OpenGL is our graphic specification
所以我们使用OpenGL然后把数据作为纹理发送到显卡
so we use OpenGL to then send that data into the GPU as a texture
一旦我们做了那个，当它在绘制时，就可以修改着色器来读取那个纹理
once we've done that, we can modify our shader to actually read that texture, when it's drawing
所以像素着色器，也就是片段着色器会从纹理内存中读取
so the pixel shader the fragment shader is going to read from that texture memory
并实际计算出每个像素应该是什么，构成那个纹理每部分的颜色是什么
and actually work out which pixel should be, which color as per that texture
那就是当我们绘制出矩形的时候会发生的事情
and that's what will happen when we actually draw that rectangle of ours
那么我们来回顾一下
so just to recap over all of that
中间还有一些详细的步骤可以解决这个问题
and there are some detailed steps kind of in between that will address definitely
但那就是它的要点，对吧
but that is the gist of it, right
我们载入图像，在OpenGL中创建纹理
we load our image, we create a texture in OpenGL
然后，当渲染的时候，我们必须绑定纹理
we then have to bind that texture, when it's time to render
我们修改我们的着色器来绑定到那个纹理插槽
we modify our shader to all sort of bind to that texture slot
那就是我们要绑定我们纹理的地方
that we've bound our texture to
我们也在着色器中对这个纹理采样
and we also sample that texture in our shader
当我们绘制矩形时，我们应该看到纹理
and when we draw our rectangle, we should see the texture
那么就让我们直接写一些代码吧
so let's just go ahead and write some code
所以我们要做的第一件事就是
so the first thing that we really need to do
加载这个图像到CPU内存中，这样我们就能把它发送到OpenGL
is load this image somehow into our CPU memory, so that we can send it to OpenGL
那么在这儿，打开的是一个github库，我会把链接放在下面的描述中
so over here, what I've got, is a github repository, which I'll link in the description below
这个里面就是stb库，这个就是c/c++的单一文件公共域库
and inside this kind of stb library, which single file public domain libraries for c/c++
所以你可以完全免费使用它
so you can use this completely free
这儿有个东西叫stb_image，我们只需要这个文件
there's something called stb_image, and really there's just this one file that's all we need
打开文件，点击这儿这个Raw
I'm going to open that file, I'm going to click on Raw here
只是为了方便自己
and just to make this really simple for myself
按control a+c，那么我复制了这个文件中的所有文本
I'm just going to control a control c, so I'm copying all the text inside this file here
回到我的项目中，我要在这里新建一个源文件
and back inside of my project, I'm going to make a new source file here
现在我要创建一个名为vendor的文件夹
now I'm going to make a folder called vendor
在里面，创建一个叫stb_image的文件夹
and inside there, a folder called stb_image
这样我就能知道这不是我的代码
just so that I can kind of know that this isn't really my code
然后创建一个头文件stb_image.h
I'll make a header file called stb_image.h
并且删除这个文件中的一切，只粘贴我刚才复制的
and delete everything from this file, and just paste in what I've copied
你们可以看到，这儿大概有7.5k行代码
and you can see, it's about seven and a half thousand lines of code here
好了，酷，现在如果你们实际去阅读这个文件，那是你们应该做的
okay, cool, now if you actually read this file, this is what you should do
当你们从互联网和新库等等上获得新的文件
when you when you get new files from the internet and new libraries and all that
它基本上是说实现这个很简单，对吧
it basically says pretty simply do this, right
在包含这个文件之前定义STB_IMAGE_IMPLEMENTATION
define STB_IMAGE_IMPLEMENTATION before you include this file in one
在c++文件中创建实现，好了
see your c++ file to create the implementation, okay
那么它应该看起来像这样
so it should look like this
它甚至好像给了你们一个例子，对吧
it even like gives you an example, right
所以为了编译这段代码一次我们需要做的，而且只编译一次
so what we need to do to actually compile this code once, and once only
基本上就是添加一个新项，添加一个cpp文件
is we basically add a new item, I'm going to add a cpp file
我就叫这个stb_image，就是stb_image.cpp，然后包含stb_image.h
I'm going to call this stb_image, call stb_image.cpp, I'm going to include stb_image.h
但在此之前，正如这里所说，将定义STB_IMAGE_IMPLEMENTATION
but before I do that, as it says over here, I'm going to define STB_IMAGE_IMPLEMENTATION
那就是我要做的
and that's all I need to do
如果我按control+f7，它会编译所有的stb_image代码
and if I hit control f7, it's going to compile all of that stb_image code
就这样，完成了，就那么简单
there we go, done, simple as that
现在，下一步是为我们自己创建Texture类
now the next step is going to be the created Texture class for ourselves
我们可以组织所有的代码
that we can kind of organize over all of our code
那么我要添加一个新项，它将是一个头文件
so I'm going to add a new item, it's going to be a header file
就叫它Texture.h
we're going to call it Texture.h
我还要添加一个新项
I'm also going to add a new item
这将是我们的cpp文件，当然就是Texture.cpp
which is going to be our cpp file, of course Texture.cpp
在这儿包含Texture.h
going to include Texture.h in here
这就是我们的Texture类
and this is just going to be our Texture class
我会在这儿包含Renderer
I'll include the Renderer in here
这样我们就能访问OpenGL和我们需要的一切
so that we have access to OpenGL and everything we need
我们可以开始创建我们的Texture类
and we can start with creating our Texture class
那么在这里，我把它设为m_RendererID，就像我们对所有东西做的那样
so inside here, I'll make it m_RendererID, as we have for pretty much everything
我还会跟踪纹理的实际文件路径(m_FilePath)
I'm also going to keep track of the actual file path of our texture
我要定义一个unsigned char，它将是我们的m_LocalBuffer
I'm going to define an unsigned char, which is going to be our m_LocalBuffer
这将是纹理的本地存储
so this is just going to be local storage for the texture
最后，我们还需要宽度(m_Width)和高度(m_Height)
and then finally, we also need the width and the height
以及实际纹理的每像素位(m_BPP)
and the bits per pixel of the actual texture
好了，酷，然后在public里面，我要创建一个构造方法
all right, cool, and then inside here public, I'm going to make a constructor
它只接收一个路径(path)，那就是我们所需要的
which is just going to take in a path, that's all we need
我也会创建一个析构方法，这样我们就能在需要的时候销毁一切
I'll make a destruct as well, so that we can destroy everything when we need to
还有一个叫Bind的方法，以及Unbind，现在差不多了
a function called Bind and Unbind, that's pretty much it, now
我会做一些辅助方法，比如GetWidth
I will make some like helpers here, like GetWidth for example
这会返回宽度和高度，以防万一，我们以后想要得到那个
which will just return width and height, just in case, we want to get that later
但总的来说，我喜欢添加这些东西
but in general, I like to kind of add these things
因为我真的需要它们，而不是找我所有的类
as I actually need them, instead of pretty finding all my class
否则，光是思考就会花上一段时间
because otherwise, it takes quite a while to just think about
我想知道我想要这个类有什么
well I wonder what I want this class to have
当你们以后可以扩展它的时候
when you can just extend it later
现在就是Bind，我要做一点改变
now Bind, I'm going to change a little bit
我要在这里放一个unsigned int slot = 0，那么这是一个可选参数
I'm actually going to put an unsigned int slot equals 0 over here, so what this is is an optional parameter
如果你们不指定它，它将是0
if you don't specify that, it will be 0
它基本上允许你们指定这个slot, 那就是你们想要绑定纹理的插槽
which basically allows you to specify the slot, that you want to bind a texture to
现在在OpenGL中，我们有各种各样的插槽可以绑定纹理
now in OpenGL, we have various slots that we can bind textures to
那个存在的原因是，因为我们有能力一次性绑定多个纹理
and the reason that exists is, because we have the ability to actually bind more than one texture at once
那么在Windows上，典型的现代显卡，你们会有32个纹理插槽
so on Windows, typically in with modern GPUs, you have about 32 textures slots
而在移动设备上，比如android或iPhone
whereas on mobile, like on an android or an iphone
你们可能有比如八个插槽，这取决于你们的实际显卡
you might have like eight for example again, this really depends on the actual GPU that you have
以及它们的OpenGL实现，你们总是可以询问OpenGL
and their implementation of OpenGL, you can always ask for OpenGL
嘿，我有多少纹理槽
hey, how many textures slots do I have
只会给你们一个大概的数字，在Windows上，现代GPU，大约32个
just to give you a rough ballpark, on Windows, on modern GPU, you have about 32
在移动显卡上，你们可能有8个，那大概就是它的情况
on mobile GPU, you may have 8, that's roughly what it will be
当然，你们可以咨询你们的平台来找到答案
but of course, you can just consult your platform to find out
那么我右键点击Texture, 使用VS助手，创建所有的方法实现
so I'm going to right click on Texture, and using visual assistant, just create all of the method implementations
这将为我的构造和所有方法创建这些实现
that's just going to create these implementations for my construction and all of my methods
我将在构造方法中，将filePath指定为path
I'm going to in my constructor, assign filePath to be path
我想设置初始化这些东西
I want to set basically initialize most of these things
m_LocalBuffer将设置为nullptr，宽度(m_Width)高度(m_Height)为0
m_LocalBuffer will set to nullptr, width height to 0
你们真的应该试着用同样的方法来做这个
and you should really try and do this in the same thing
我在m_BPP中的定义，m_BPP(0)
what I'm defined in m_BPP, m_BPP to 0
看起来很不错，所以我唯一做的就是
and that looks pretty good, so the only thing I really did was
实际上我是按顺序做的
actually I did do it in order
把它(m_RendererID)写成第一个0
and write it was the first thing 0
好了，酷，那么继续，我们得到了一些，我在初始化所有的变量
alright cool so there we go I've got some, I'm initializing all of my variables
然后我要做的就是开始加载纹理
and then what I'm going to do here is just start loading the texture
那么我会使用GLCall(glGenTextures())
so I'm going to use GLCall glGenTextures
第一个参数是1，生成一个纹理，并且赋值到m_RendererID
1, generate one texture, and assign it to RendererID
然后我要直接绑定它
I'm then going to go ahead and bind it
那么我们可以通过调用glBindTexture来绑定它
so we bind it by just calling glBindTexture
现在我们指定，就像对顶点缓冲区所做的那样，当实际绑定它的时候
now we specify kind of like what we do with our vertex buffer, when where we actually bind it
我们指定它是哪种类型的缓冲区，或者在哪个插槽运行它
we specify kind of which what kind of buffer it is, or what slot with running it to
所以在这个例子中，这将是一个GL_TEXTURE_2D
so in this case, this is going to be a GL_TEXTURE_2D
因为它只是一个二维的纹理
because it's just a two dimensional texture
我们以后可能会讨论不同的纹理类型，当我们接触它们的时候
we might talk about the different texture types in the future, when we get to them
RendererID就是我们绑定的纹理，现在让我们直接来加载图像
RendererID is the texture that we're binding, now let's go ahead and actually load our image
那么要做到这一点，我们需要包含stb_image，所以我要输入include
so to do that, we need to include stb_image, so I'm just going to type in include
提示一下，当然是在vendor/stb_image中，那就是stb_image
as a tip now, of course is gonna be in vendor/stb_image, that's stb_image
如果我实际正确地设置了这个项目
if I was actually properly setting up this project
我可能实际上已经在编译器的包含部分中包含了vendor文件夹
I might have actually included the vendor folder in the include parts for my compiler
这样我就可以不用写vendor了，不过这也没关系
so that I wouldn't have to kind of do vendor, but this is fine
实际上，在我们做这些之前，先让我们实际加载图像
now actually, before we do all of this, let's actually load the image
现在我要做的第一件事是输入stbi_set_flip_vertically_on_load
now the first thing I want to do is type in stbi_set_flip_vertically_on_load
现在我们需要这样做的原因，然后我要把这个设为1
now the reason we need to do this, and then I'm going to just set this to 1
那么这实际上是垂直翻转我们的纹理
so what this does is actually flips our texture vertically
所以它是颠倒的，我们这么做的原因是
so it makes it upside down, the reason we need to do this is
因为OpenGL希望我们的纹理像素从左下角开始
because OpenGL actually expects our texture pixels to kind of start at the bottom left
不是左上角，对吧，OpenGL的左下角坐标就是(0, 0)
not the top left, right, so the bottom left in OpenGL is 0 0
现在通常当我们加载像png这样的图像
now typically when we load images like png
比如把它存储在扫描行中，从图像的顶部到底部
for example stores it in scan lines kind of, from the top of the image to the bottom of the image
所以实际上我们需要在加载时翻转它
so we need to actually flip it on load
这真的取决于你们的纹理格式，所以一定要看看这个
this really does depend on your texture format, so definitely take a look at this
对于我们的用例，对于这里的png，我们确实需要翻转它
for our use case, for our png here, we do need to flip it
所以如果你们看到你们的纹理是上下颠倒的
so just if you see that your texture is upside down or whatever
你们可以设置这个标志，以确保你们得到正确的方式
you can play with this flag to make sure that you get it the right way up
好了，下一件事我们要做的是赋值m_LocalBuffer
okay, the next thing we're going to do is assign m_LocalBuffer
就是我们的纹理的本地存储，是stbi_load(赋给m_LocalBuffer)
which is our local storage for our texture, to be stbi_load
现在我们需要指定文件名，也就是path.c_str()
now we're going to have to specify a file name, which is just going to be path.c_str()
然后我们有指向x和y通道的指针
then we have pointers to x and y channels
就是存储了我们实际的宽度和高度，诸如此类的
which is just going to store all of our actual width and height, and all that
那么我们已经为这个创建了变量，我们只是传递内存地址
so we've already created variables for this, we're just passing the memory address
这个stbi_load函数所做的就是写入
and what this stbi_load function will do is actually write
宽度，高度，每像素位等等
the width and height and the bits per pixel or whatever
（为我们写入）到那些实际的变量，所以我们传入这些变量的指针
into those actual variables for us, so we're passing pointers to these variables
这样这个函数就能写入到它们中去
so that this function can actually write to them
预期通道就是我们有多少个预期（颜色）通道
and desired channels is kind of how many desired channels we have
那么想要使用RGBA，所以那是4，所以只需要像那样输入4，好了
so we want RGBA, so that's 4, so I just want to type in 4 like that, okay
那么一旦我们有了这个，我们实际上就有了在这个LocalBuffer中所有的纹理数据
so once we've got this, we've actually got all of our texture data inside this LocalBuffer here
我现在需要做的是设置一些实际的设置
what I need to do now is set up some actual settings
我猜就是对于我们刚刚生成的纹理
I guess for our texture that we've just generated here
那么我们设置任何纹理参数的方式，就是调用glTextParameter
so the way that we set any texture parameters, we call glTextParameter
然后是我们要设置的数据类型，那么这个就是i，表示整数
and then the type of data we're trying to set, so this is going to be an i, for integer
第一个参数是目标GL_TEXTURE_2D，下一个参数是实际的参数名
so the first parameter here is the target which is TEXTURE_2D, the next slot is the actual parameter name
在这个例子中是GL_TEXTURE_MIN_FILTER
which in this case is going to be GL_TEXTURE_MIN_FILTER
那么这是缩小过滤器，这就是我们的纹理将如何被模拟下来
so this is the minification filter, this is how our texture will actually be resembled down
如果它需要被渲染的比它的像素要小
if it needs to be rendered smaller than it is kind of per pixel
我们会有一期关于深入了解所有这些纹理参数的视频
we're going to have an in depth episode on all of these kind of texture parameters
因为就像处理MIT地图，放大和放大过滤
because like dealing with MIT maps and kind of magnification and magnification filtering
就像你们知道的边缘缩小所有这些
and like you know edge clamping all of that
这是一个很大的话题，我就不想塞在这里了
is it kind of a big topic, then I don't want to just squeeze it in here
所以我们以后会更详细地讨论这个东西
so we will talk about the stuff in more detail and the future
别担心，但现在，你们可以使用这些设置，我会边做边解释的
don't worry, but for now, you can just kind of use these settings, and I'll explain them as I go
那么我们将这个设置为GL_LINEAR，也就是线性重新取样
so this we're gonna set to GL_LINEAR, which is just going to linearly resample everything
所以看起来还是不错的
so it will kind of still look okay
它不会在最近的像素上断开，这是GL_LINEAR，我们会做的
it's not gonna snap at the nearest pixel, which is what GL_LINEAR, us would do
我们还必须指定放大过滤器
we also have to specify the magnification filter
也就是如果我们在一个区域上渲染纹理
which is if we actually kind of render our texture on an area
那比实际的纹理大小更大，所以它需要放大
that is larger in pixels than the actual texture size, so it needs to scale it up
我们还需要指定嵌入模式
we also need to specify the clamp mode
那么就是glTextParameteri(GL_TEXTURE_2D, GL_TEXTURE_WRAP)
so glTextParameteri GL_TEXTURE_2D GL_TEXTURE_WRAP
现在我称它们为嵌入模式，但它们实际上是环绕模式
now I call them clamp modes, but they're just, they're really wrap modes
那么WRAP_S就是水平环绕，所以我们想要它嵌入
so WRAP_S is the horizontal wrap, so we want it to clamp
这意味着我们基本上不希望它扩大区域，另一个选项是平铺
which means that we want it to basically not extend the area, the other option is tiling
所以我们不想在这里平铺纹理，那么S&T是有点像x和y
so we don't want to tile our textures here, so S and T is kind of like x and y
但是对于纹理，你们需要指定这四个参数，如果你们不指定这四个参数
but for textures, and these four parameters you need to specify, if you don't specify these four parameters
只会得到像一个黑色的纹理，这有点烦人
you're just gonna get it like a black texture, which is a little bit annoying
因为你们希望它们是无意识的默认值，默认情况下，但它们不是
because you kind of expect them to maybe be insensible defaults, by default, but they're not
所以一定要指定这四个参数，否则你们可能会得到一个黑色纹理
so make sure you specify these four, otherwise you may probably will get a black texture
但当然，这取决于你们的OpenGL实现
but of course that does depend on your OpenGL implementation
好了，酷，下一步是给OpenGL我们在这里读取到的数据
okay, cool, next step is going to be to actually give OpenGL the data that we've read in here
那么我们已经在m_LocalBuffer中有了一些像素数据
so we've got a bunch of pixel data inside m_LocalBuffer
我们现在把它发送到OpenGL
let's actually send it now to OpenGL
那么实现那个的方式是通过一个叫做glTextImage2d的OpenGL函数
so the way that we do that is via an OpenGL called called glTextImage2d
所以目标是GL_TEXTURE_2D
so the target is going to be GL_TEXTURE_2D
这个level参数，在这一点上
the level, this is at this point
你可能需要阅读文档来了解所有这些参数
you probably want to read the documentation to figure out what all of these are
其中很多参数与我们完全无关，我跳过那些
a lot of these are completely irrelevant to us, I'm going to kind of skip past that
我们将在以后看看高级纹理，那么就会讲到那些
we will look at advanced textures in the future, so we'll cover them then
但现在我们想让level为0，因为这不是一个复合纹理
but for now we want the level to be 0, because this is not a multi level texture
内部格式将是GL_RGBA
internal format is going to be GL_RGBA
这是OpenGL看到我们实际格式的方式
that's how OpenGL is going to see our actual format
RGBA不是我们提供的数据格式
RGBA not the format of the data we're supplying
而是我们希望OpenGL如何处理我们的数据
but how we want OpenGL to deal with our data
内部格式与格式本身就是一个巨大的主题
internal format versus format is a huge topic in itself
甚至这也需要单独占用一期，因为人们总是混淆这一点
which will probably even dedicate an episode too, because people confuse that all the time
但是内部格式，也就是第一种格式，那是OpenGL存储纹理数据的方式
but internal format, which is the first format, that's how OpenGL will store your texture data
而格式是纹理数据，是你们提供给OpenGL的数据格式
whereas format is the texture data, is the format of the data you're providing OpenGL with
那么换句话说，也就是m_LocalBuffer的格式
so in other words, the format of m_LocalBuffer
在最近的OpenGL实现中，你们实际上应该叫它GL_RGBA8，好了
now in recent implementations of OpenGL, you should actually call this GL_RGBA8, okay
那么应该指定每个通道的实际比特数
so you should be specifying the actual bits per channel
就是你希望OpenGL如何存储你的纹理
which is how you want to OpenGL to store your texture
所以GL_RGBA是一种被弃用的，但它仍将在大多数实现上工作
so GL_RGBA is kind of deprecated, it will still work on most implementations
除了你们实现的，但严格来说，现代OpenGL完成这个正确的方法是
but you do, technically, the correct modern OpenGL way to do this is
实际上就是在这里指定一个数字，也就是每个通道有多少比特
actually to specify a number here, which says how many bits you have per channel
好了，那么width就是m_Width
allright, so width is going to be m_Width
这是我们从stbi_load函数中读取到的
which is what we read in from our stbi_load function
然后我们传递一个m_Height作为我们纹理的高度
then we pass an m_Height for the height of our texture
至于边框，而我们绝对不需要边框，所以就是零像素边框
border, we definitely don't want a border, so zero pixel border
那么格式就是第二种格式
so format is that's like the second format
就是我们提供的数据格式
that's the format of the data we're supplying
就是GL_RGBA，我们这里不用数字
GL_RGBA, what it is we don't use numbers here
类型是数据的类型，也就是GL_UNSIGNED_BYTE，对吧
the type is the type of data, so unsigned byte, right
那么我们有GL_RGBA，每个通道都是一个无符号字节
so we have GL_RGBA, and each one of these channels is an unsigned byte
最后，我们指定了像素，现在你们可以做这个了
and then finally, we have appointed to pixels, now you can make this
你们可以在这里传递一个空指针，0或类似的东西
you can actually pass in a null pointer here, 0 or something like that
如果你们在这个阶段还没有准备好把你们的数据给OpenGL
if you're not ready at this stage to actually give OpenGL your data
那意味着你们只是在显存上分配空间
what that means is that you're just allocating space on the GPU
因为它知道那个需要多少空间
because it knows how much space it needs
但是你们并没有给它提供数据，现在我们已经有了数据
but you're not actually providing it with data, now we already have the data
我们会传入m_LocalBuffer，就像那样
so we're just gonna pass in m_LocalBuffer, just like that
很好，那就是我们所需要的
allright great, and that's really all we need
那么我现在要做的是通过调用glBindTexture(0)来解绑我们的纹理
so what I want to do now is unbind our texture by just calling glBindTexture 0
也可以调用UnbindTextureFunc
could also call the UnbindTextureFunc
我们当然需要指定我们想要解绑的东西，那么就是GL_TEXTURE
well we of course need to specify what we want to unbind, so GL_TEXTURE
因为我今天有这段代码
today since I've got this code here
我要复制这个，然后把它也解绑
I'm just going to copy and face this into unbind as well
因为那就是我们需要的，酷
because that's really all we need, cool
现在我们能做的是，如果m_LocalBuffer，对吧
so now what we can do is if m_LocalBuffer, right
那么如果这个缓冲区确实包含数据
so if this buffer does actually contain data
我们会用stbi_image_free来释放这个LocalBuffer
we're going to use stbi_image_free to actually free this LocalBuffer
现在在更复杂的设置中
now in more complicated setups
你们可能希望在CPU上保留像素数据的副本
you may want to retain a copy of the pixel data on your CPU
因为你们可能想要对它进行抽样或进行其他的操作
because you might want to sample it or do something
不管你们想怎么处理这些数据
whatever you may want to do with that data
所以那是非常完美的，好了
so that's totally perfectly, okay, as well totally perfectly, okay
那也是可以接受的，对吧
that's also kind of acceptable, right
所以你们可能想在构造方法中
so you may want to have something something in the constructor
那就像，你们知道的，保存本地数据之类的
that's like, you know, keep local data around or something like that
我们不关心这个，所以我就直接释放它
we don't really care about that, so I'm just freeing it
这就是为什么我把这个设为成员变量m_LocalBuffer
but that's why I kind of made this a member variable m_LocalBuffer
以防你们想要存储它，就是那样
in case you kind of want to store it, and that's it
最后，在析构方法中，我们可以删除那个数据
now finally over here inside our destructor, we could delete the data
现在我们已经释放了构造方法中的数据
now we've already freed the data in the constant in the constructor
所以我们不需要在这里处理那个
so we don't have to deal with that here
但我们确实需要glDeleteTexture从显卡中删除我们的实际纹理
but we do need to actually glDeleteTexture to delete our actual texture from the GPU
当此对象实例被销毁时
when this object guests destroy
所以我们只要glDeleteTextures，并传入那个RendererID
so we'll just glDeleteTextures and pass in that RendererID
现在Bind是一个有趣的函数
now Bind is an interesting function
因为我们已经知道如何绑定纹理，它真的只是这样，对吧
because we already know how to bind textures, it's really just this, right
但这里我们能做的实际上就是指定一个纹理槽
but what we can do here is actually specify a texture slot
我们通过输入GLCall(glActiveTexture)来实现那个
and we do that by typing in GLCall glActiveTexture
现在ActiveTexture取一个整数，这是一个真正的GLenum
now ActiveTexture takes in an integer, which is this really a GLenum
将是我们当前激活的那个纹理插槽
which is going to be which texture slot we're currently activating
所以再说一次，这有点像OpenGL上的整个状态机选择
so again, this is kind of like the whole state machine selecting thing on OpenGL
我们会说，嘿，我要创建glActiveTexture(16)
we basically say, hey, I'm going to make glActiveTexture slot 16
那意味着我绑定的下一个纹理将绑定到16号插槽上
that means that the next texture that I bind will be bound to slot 16
直到我用一个不同的插槽再次调用glActiveTexture
until I call glActiveTexture again with a different slot
所以在这种情况下，我们指定插槽的方法是用减号，对吧
so in this case, the way that we specify slots is we use minus, right
那么GL_TEXTURE_ZERO是第一个插槽
so GL_TEXTURE_ZERO like that is the very first slot
现在我们有纹理1，纹理2等等，如果你仔细观察它们等于什么
now we have texture 1, texture 2, whatever, if you actually look at what these are equal to
它们当然只是整数，一直到31，对吧
they are of course just integers, and they go all the way up to 31, right
那么你们有32个纹理插槽
so you have 32 texture slots
这并不意味着你们的平台支持那个
now this does not mean that your platform supports that
许多纹理只有32恰好是OpenGL规格允许的最大值
many textures is just 32 happens to be the maximum that OpenGL that the OpenGL specification allows
你们的平台，如我所说的手机可能支持8个
your platform as I said mobile may have like 8
所以你们应该查询并找出你们有多少纹理插槽
so you should query and find out how many you have
如果你们打算使用这么多纹理插槽
if you are going to use this many texture slots
通常情况下，除非你们制作的是一款真正大型的游戏，否则不会这么做
but you probably usually won't be unless you're making a really big game
因为有很多方法可以使用，你知道的，比如重用纹理
because there are ways to kind of you know reuse textures
我们稍后会讲到，不管怎样，我们有所有的纹理插槽
and we'll talk about that later, but anyway, we have all the textures slot
在这个例子中，我们指定了一个无符号整型
now in this case, we are specifying an unsigned int
这个大概是0到31
now this will be something like 0 through through the 31
你们能做的就是输入GL_TEXTURE_ZERO加上slot，然后它添加这个slot
so what you can do is just type in GL_TEXTURE_ZERO plus slot, and then it will add the slot
因为如果你们看这些定义
because if you look at these definitions
你们可以看到它们实际上是连续的数字，对吧，它们只是在增加
you can see that they are actually consecutive numbers, right, they do just count up
所以那就是我们的整个Texture类
so that's our entire Texture class
这就是我们需要的全部，就是glActiveTexture，渲染它和所有这些
that is all that we need to actually is glActiveTexture, and for us to render it and all of that
好吧，我知道这一期会很长
alright, so I knew this was gonna be a long episode
让我们继续，让我们实际在屏幕上看到一些东西
but let's keep going, and let's actually see something on the screen
因为那就是今天视频的目标
because that is the goal for today's video
那么回到Application文件，让我们设置所有这些
so back inside Application, let's set all this up
那么我在任何时候都只需要输入Texture texture
so I'm going to at any point really just type in Texture texture
我给它的路径是textures/ChernoLogo.png
I'm gonna give it the path which is read such textures/ChernoLogo.png
我将在顶部包含Texture，因为我还没有这样做
I'm going to include Texture at the top, because I haven't done that yet
然后向下滚动，我要绑定我的纹理，我不会传入参数
and scrolling back down, I'm going to bind my texture, I'm not gonna pass in the parameter
也就是说默认值是0
which means it's gonna be called 0 by default
顺便说一句，我还有件事要做
one thing I need to do, by the way
对于我的这个Shader，在我忘记之前，我们需要首先修复
with my Shader before I forget is we need to first of all fix out
我上次犯的一个可怕的错误
this awful error I made last time in which I passed in
我基本上创建了有一个无符号到整型的映射
and well basically I make this map have an unsigned to int
看起来我只是我使用无符号整型有点太多了
and I just I use unsigned int a bit too much, it seems
因为只有GetUniformLocation函数
because just GetUniformLocation function
我甚至检查一下location是否为-1
I even check to see if the location is -1 here
因为这是完全有效的，这意味着它找不到我们的统一变量
because that's totally valid, that just means that it couldn't find our uniform
但这里我把它赋值给了一个无符号整数，它显然永远不会是-1
but I'm assigning it to an unsigned int here, which is obviously never going to be -1
所有这些都应该是整型，而不是无符号整型
so all of this should be an int, not an unsigned int
当你们处理OpenGL中统一变量的位置时
when you're dealing with uniform locations in OpenGL
类型是32位整数，好了，所以就是整型，这个也应该是整型
the type is a 32 bit integer, okay, so int and this should also be int
如果我们回到头文件
and if we go back to our header file
这应该是int，因为这是我们的统一变量的缓存
this should be int, because that's our uniform cache
而且这个应该是整型的，我想这就是所有的整型了
and also this should be int, and I think that's all the ints
如果我编译这个，希望能运行一丢丢，是的，我们都很好
if I compile this, hope little work, and yep we're all good
好了，那就是我需要澄清的一件事
okay, that's one thing I need to clear up
我们现在需要做的一件事是我们需要告诉我们的着色器
now, one thing that we need to do is we need to actually tell our shader
从哪个纹理插槽取样，我们这样做的方法是通过一个统一变量
which texture slot to sample from, and the way that we do that is via a uniform
现在这并不是一个整数插槽，而是一个采样插槽
now this isn't really an integer slot, it's something called a sampler slot
这有点模糊，有点奇怪
and this is a bit hazy and a bit weird
基本上我们需要做的是发送一个整数统一变量到我们的着色器
basically what we need to do is send an integer uniform to our shader
那个整数是我们绑定了纹理到我们想要取样的那个插槽
and that integer is the slot that we've bound a texture to that we want to sample from
然后在着色器代码中，我们可以使用那个采样器或者传入的那个整数
and then in the shader code, we can actually use that sampler or that integer that we've passed in
对纹理进行取样，然后做我们想做的，对吧
to actually sample that texture and do what we want with it, okay
所以那就是它的工作原理
so that's how that works
那么为了做到这一点，我们需要在这里写另一个着色器统一变量函数
so to do that, we need to write another shader uniform function here
也就是SetUniform1i，它代表整数
which is going to be called SetUniform1i, which is for integer
然后我们取一个这样的整数值，复制粘贴这个1f函数
and then we take an inter value like that, I'll copy and paste this 1f function
然后用int替换这个，差不多就是这样了，对吧
and replace this with int and that's pretty much it, right
一定要把这里的1f换成1i，好了
just make sure you replace uniform 1f here with 1i, okay
酷，回到Application文件，我们有了这个
cool, back to application, so that we have this
我们实际也可以把它设置好
we can actually set that up as well
那么就是shader.SetUniform1i("u_Texture")
so shader.SetUniform1i, we're going to call this uniform u_Texture
我们会把它设为0，因为我们把纹理绑定到插槽0
and we're going to set it to 0, okay, because we've bound our texture to slot 0
所以0需要匹配你们这儿传入的任何东西
so that 0 needs to match whatever you're passing in here
如果我把纹理2之类的东西传给插槽2
if I had passed in like texture bound 2 or something to slot 2
我们会在这里传入2，好了，让我们撤销它，很好，酷
we would be passing in 2 here, okay, let's undo that, alright cool
好了，很简单的东西，现在还有一件事我们没做过
so there we go, pretty simple stuff, now, one thing we haven't done
实际上就是创建了一个叫做纹理坐标的东西
is actually created something called texture coordinates
那么我们需要使用一个叫做TextureCoordinateSystem的东西
so what we need to do is actually use something called a TextureCoordinateSystem
告诉我们的几何图形，我们渲染的是纹理的哪一部分来采样
to tell our geometry that we're rendering which part of the texture to sample from
所以我们的像素着色器通过渲染并分解我们的矩形，对吧
so our pixel shader goes through and renders and factorizes our rectangle, right
只是遍历矩形并绘制每个像素
just goes through the rectangle and draws every pixel
像素着色器或片段着色器负责确定每个像素的颜色
the pixel shader or the fragment shader is responsible for determining the color of each pixel
所以在某种程度上，我们真正需要做的是，在渲染某个像素的时候
so what we actually need to do is somehow, when it's up to rendering a certain pixel
告诉它对纹理的某个区域进行采样，以检索像素应该是什么颜色
tell it to sample a certain area of our texture to retrieve what color the pixel should be
对吧，如果你们仔细想想，这其实很简单，并不复杂到难以理解
right, if you think about it, it's actually kind of simple, it's not too complicated to understand
希望这会有意义，如果你们不往下扔硬币的话
hopefully this makes sense, if you don't drop a coin below
我可能会做一个关于原始关系如何运行的视频
and I might make a detailed kind of in depth video on how the raw relation works
以及纹理采样是如何工作的等等
and how texture sampling works and all that stuff
但基本上我想说的是我们需要这么说
but basically what I'm saying is we need to say that
屏幕上矩形的左下角是坐标(0, 0)
hey, the bottom left of our rectangle on our screen is like coordinate 0 0
右边的顶部是纹理的另一端
and the top like right is the other end of the texture
在OpenGL中就是(1, 1)
which in OpenGL terms is going to be 1 1
好了，因为纹理并没有真正地将纹理绑定到特定的大小
okay, because textures don't really literally tie textures to certain sizes
我们不会将纹理坐标绑定到特定的分辨率
we don't tie texture coordinates to a certain resolution
因为纹理可以是64x64
because the texture could be 64 by 64
可以是1024x1024，可以是57x19，可以是任何分辨率的，对吧
it could be 1024 by 1024, it could be like 57 by 19, it could be anything, right
所以我们需要做的就是指定矩形中的每个顶点
so what we need to do is basically specify for each vertex that we have of our rectangle
什么区域的纹理应该是什么
what area of the texture should be
然后片段着色器会在这之间插入，所以如果我们进入一个像素
and then the fragment shader will interpolate between that, so that if we're entering a pixel
这就像是在两个顶点之间，它会选择纹理坐标
that's like halfway between two vertices, it will pick the texture coordinates
它就像是，你们知道的，在两个顶点的中间
it's like, you know, halfway between the two vertices
让我们可以设置那个，为了做到那一点，如果来到这里到我们的位置
let's set that up, so to do that, if we come over here into our positions
我们知道这个1在左下角
we know this 1 is the bottom left
它将是(0, 0)，我添加了另一个vec2
that's going to be 0 by 0, I'm adding another vec2 basically
我给每个顶点添加了两个浮点数，这是我们的纹理坐标
I'm adding two more floats to each vertex here, which are our texture coordinates
这是(1.0, 0.0)，因为这是在右边，对吧
now this is going to be 1.0 0.0, because it's the right side, right
那么0.5f是矩形最右边的边缘位置
so 0.5f is the right most edge of our actual rectangle
我把它设为1，这意味着从纹理的右边取样
and so I'm setting that to be 1, which means sample from the right side of the texture
这是1.0，而右上方也是(0.5, 0.5)
this is going to be 1.0, when 1.0, as well 0.5 0.5 is the top right
那也是我们在没有纹理坐标的情况下匹配的
and that's what we're also matching without texture coordinate
最后，我们有0和1.0
and then finally, we have 0 and 1.0
现在需要把这个添加到VertexBufferLayout，通过我们的接口，很简单
now we need to add this to our VertexBufferLayout again, with our api, it's really easy
我们只需要做这个layout推入两个浮点数
we just do this layout push two more floats
对吧，就这样，这就是我们需要做的
right, that's it, that's all we need to do
我们还需要扩展这个VertexBuffer来包含这些额外的东西，对吧
we also need to actually expand this VertexBuffer to contain these extra things, right
所以现在不是每个顶点有两个浮点数
so now instead of having two floats per vertex
实际上每个顶点有四个浮点数，所以我们把它增加到四个
we actually have four floats per vertex, so we'll increase this to four
最后我们需要进入Shader，基本上重写整个东西
and finally we need to go into our Shader, and basically rewrite the whole thing
那么在我们的VertexShader中，我们现在在位置1处取一个纹理坐标
so in our VertexShader, we now take in a texture coordinate at location one
也就是一个矢量，或者叫它textCoord之类的
which is a vector or call it, I don't know, a textCoord or something like that
现在我们要面对一些新的东西
and now we're faced with something a little bit new
我们需要把这个纹理坐标放到我们实际的片段着色器中
we need to get this texture coordinate into our actual fragment shader
因为看看这个，就像我之前说的，我们取样纹理的方法是
because check this out, the way that we're going to actually sample our texture is, as I said earlier
通过使用sampler2D，对吧
by using that sampler2D uniform, right
那么就是uniform sampler2D u_Texture，也就是我们在这里设置的统一纹理
so sampler2D u_Texture, which is the uniform that we set over here
我们设它为0，对吧，那么我们需要对它进行采样
we set it to be 0, right, so we need to sample this somehow
并且这就是纹理统一变量
and that's this texture uniform
我们这样做的方法就是，我们实际计算出颜色
and the way that we do that is, we actually work out the color
这个返回的vec4，有点像我们的textColor
this returns of vec4, which is kind of like our textColor
我把这个写出来，textColor = texture()
I'll just write this out for you guys, text color is going to be texture
我们正在采样的纹理是u_Texture
the texture that we're sampling which is u_Texture
然后我们需要指定那些纹理坐标，对吧
and then we need to specify those texture coordinates, right
我们如何指定我们的纹理坐标
so how do we actually specify our texture coordinates
因为它们在顶点着色器中
because they're in the vertex shader
我们在顶点和片段着色器之间发送数据的方式
so the way that we kind of send data between the vertex and the fragment shaders
就是通过叫Varying的东西，在现代OpenGL中
by something called a Varying, now in modern OpenGL
这是一种我们已经习惯了的输入输出系统
this is kind of the in and out system that we're already used to
类似地，我们可以通过输入数据到顶点着色器中通过输入in
similarly to how we can actually input data into the vertex shader by typing it in
同时从片段着色器输出数据通过标记它为out
and also output data from the fragment shader by having it out
也可以将数据从顶点着色器输出到片段着色器中，我们这样做的方式
we can also output data from the vertex shader into the fragment shader, and the way that we do that
所以我们输入out
so we type in out
这将是一个vec2，当然这是我们的文本
now this is going to be a vec2 of course it's our text according it
我将这个命名为v_TextCoord, v听起来像是Varying，就是这个的名字
and I'll call this v_TextCoord, v sounds for Varying which is what this is called
然后我分配v_TextCoord等于我们从顶点缓冲区中获取的TextCoord
and then I'll assign v_TextCoord to be the TextCoord that we take in from our vertex buffer
同样在片段着色器中
and then similarly in the fragment shader
我要输入in vec2 v_TextCoord，就像这样
I'm going to type in vec2 v_TextCoord just like that
我将在这里使用textCoord
and I'm going to use that textCoord over here
这样我们就可以对特定的纹理坐标进行采样
so that we actually sample that specific texture coordinate
因为记住这个片段着色器为每个像素运行
because remember this fragment shader runs for every pixel
所以我们需要知道纹理中的精确位置来查找
so we need to know the precise location in the texture to actually look up
这样我们就可以在实际屏幕中从纹理中绘制出那个像素
so that we can draw that pixel from the texture in our actual scene
这就是采样的意义所在
and that's what this whole sampling thing is about
我相信我们以后会更深入地讨论这个问题，好了，酷
again, I'm sure we'll discuss this in the future and more depth, okay, cool
现在我不把这个赋值给u_Color，我要把这个赋值给textColor
so now instead of assigning this to u_Color, I'm going to assign this to textColor
就是我们实际的纹理查找颜色
which is our actual texture look up color
一切看起来都很好，现在我确实写了很多代码
and everything looks pretty good to me, now I did write a lot of code
我不确定这是否可行，因为我还没运行过这个程序
and I'm not sure if this will work, because I haven't even run this program once
我们按下f5，谁知道呢，也许会很漂亮
but let's just hit f5, and who knows, maybe this will just be beautiful
好了，这里我们得到了一个很好的OpenGL错误
okay, so we get nice little OpenGL error here
如果我们看看实际的控制台，我们可以看到它是1280
if we look at the actual console, we can see it's 1280
这是因为它不是GL_CLAMP
this is because this is not GL_CLAMP
在更现代的版本中，它应该是GL_CLAMP_TO_EDGE
it's supposed to be GL_CLAMP_TO_EDGE, in more modern versions
所以我们把这个设为GL_CLAMP_TO_EDGE
so we'll just set this to be GL_CLAMP_TO_EDGE
现在，我在调试的时候注意到的另一件事
now, one other thing that I noticed when I was debugging
这也是LocalBuffer实际上是null
this as well is the LocalBuffer was actually null
也就是说我们加载的不是错误的
which means we're not loading this incorrectly
那么我来刷新一下，看看我们实际的纹理发生了什么
so let me just refresh this, and figure out what's going on with our actual texture
那么我来刷新一下这个
so if I so if I just refresh this
因为某些原因，这里看起来并没有纹理
it doesn't look like we've actually got the textures in here for some reason
当然，这是因为这个res文件夹不在我的项目目录中
and that's of course because this res folder wasn't inside my project directory
确保将其放入项目目录中
make sure you put it into your project directory
如果我点击刷新按钮，你们会看到这里有纹理等等
now if I hit this refresh button, you'll see we have textures in here and all of that
所以这样效果会更好，现在按f5，取两个，好了
so this should work better, now let's hit f5, take two, alright
很美，那么我们来看看TheChernoLogo
beautiful, so we see TheChernoLogo
现在看起来就像垃圾，为什么我的标志看起来像垃圾
now it looks like absolute trash, why does my logo look like trash
我不知道我该不该留一个悬念来结束这一切
well I don't know if I should end this on a cliffhanging
或者我是否应该完成这个
or if I should actually finish this
我明显知道它为什么没运行，但这可能没问题
I know why it's not working obviously, but this could be fine
你们知道吗，我通常会留个悬念
you know what, I usually would leave this on a cliffhanger
但这一期实在是太美了，我想我们还是把它搞完吧
but this is just such a beautifully long episode that I think we might as well finish it
这是因为我没有启用混合
it's because I don't have blending enabled
当然，正如你们所看到的，ChernoLogo确实有透明的区域
and of course as you saw that ChernoLogo did have areas of transparency
那么现在没有透明渲染，没有混合
so there's no transparency being rendered right now, it's not blending at all
那就是为什么要解决这个问题会显得很奇怪
that's why it's coming out weird to fix that
我们只需要设置我们的混合函数，并启用混合
we just need to set up our blending function and enable blending
以后会有一期关于混合和透明的，我保证
there will be an episode on blending and transparency in the future, 100% guarantee that
让我们暂时把这事做好吧
let's just make this work now for the time being
那么如果我关闭这个，回到我的Application文件
so if I close this, and I go back into my Application
或者是我的Renderer
or in fact into my Renderer I think
我是否在Renderer中进行了OpenGL设置
did I do kind of OpenGL setup stuff in the Renderer
我想我没有，不，我没有
I don't think I did, no, I didn't
好了，我们现在在Application文件中做这个
okay, so we'll do this in the Application file for now
我要做的是滚动到这里
what I'm going to do is scroll up here
一旦我有了OpenGL上下文，它是OpenGL和初始化的一部分
once I have my OpenGL context, it's kind of part of the OpenGL and initialization
我想我会设置glBlendFunc，所以我要设置一个BlendFunc
I guess I'm going to set up glBlendFunc, so I'm going to set a BlendFunc
并且这个是GL_SRC_ALPHA，而不是SRC_ZERO_ALPHA
and this is going to be GL_SRC_ALPHA, not SRC_ZERO_ALPHA
就是GL_SRC_ALPHA和GL_ONE_MINUS_SRC_ALPHA
GL_SRC_ALPHA and GL_ONE_MINUS_SRC_ALPHA
所以我们现在这儿做的就是我们基本上定义了
so what we're doing here is is we're basically defining
OpenGL如何混合alpha像素，对吧
how OpenGL is going to blend alpha pixels, right
所以这真的需要单独的一期
so this really does require its own episode
但本质上，我们说的是对于src，就是取src的alpha
but essentially, we're saying that for the src, take the src alpha
当你们在上面渲染的时候
and when you're trying to render something on top of that
取1，这个src的alpha会得到它的差值
take 1, that src alpha which will basically get the difference of that
所以它真的只是
so it's just really just
它只是一个数学等式，像字面上的1
it really is just a mathematical equation, equation like literally 1
src的alpha值就是最后的dest值
the src alpha is what the dest out for is going to end up being
以后还有一期关于那个的
and get an episode on that in the future
最后，我们还需要启用混合
and then finally, we do need to also enable blending
通过调用glEnable，然后就是GL_BLEND
by calling glEnable and then GL_BLEND
好了，你们可以按任意顺序来做，这并不重要
okay, and you can do this in any order, doesn't really matter
我喜欢这样做，只是因为我们启用了混合
I kind of like doing it in this order, just because we enable blending
然后我们设置混合函数
and then we kind of set up the blend function
让我们按f5运行一下，我们应该会看到一个美丽的ChernoLogo
let's hit f5, and we should see a beautiful ChernoLogo
你们可以看到，好了，当然它现在看起来有点拉伸
and you can see, there we go, now of course it does look a bit stretched
因为我们渲染的矩形不是方形的
because the rectangle that we're rendering is not square
因为我们的窗口不是方形的
because our window is not square
这是基于窗口位置的
and this is kind of based on window positions
但如果你们能克服这一点
but if you can kind of get over that
你们就可以看到我们有一个漂亮的ChernoLogo渲染图
you can see that we have a beautiful ChernoLogo rendering
那就是我们在OpenGL中使用纹理的方式
and that is how we use textures in OpenGL
如果你们有想要得到回答任何关于纹理的问题
if you have any questions about textures that you want answered
请在下方留言
leave a comment below
因为我以后会做很多和纹理相关的视频
because I am going to make a lot of related videos to textures in the future
纹理是一个非常重要的图形编程
textures are a really big deal graphics programming and all of that
很明显，我们以后会讲到更多
obviously so we are going to talk a lot more about them in the future
除此之外，我希望你们喜欢这个视频
other than that, I hope you guys enjoyed this video
如果你们喜欢的话，可以点击那个喜欢按钮
if you did, you can hit that like button
请在下面的评论区告诉我你们的想法
and let me know what your thoughts are about all this stuff in the comment section below
和往常一样，非常感谢所有的赞助人
as always, huge thank you to all the patron supporters that
让我为你们所有人制作这样的视频
let me make videos like this for all of you
如果你们想支持这个系列，看更多的视频，提前获得视频
if you want to support this series and see more episodes and get videos early
可以访问patreon.com/TheCherno
patreon.com/TheCherno
下次见，拜
and I will see you guys next time, goodbye